# Ryan Blake Jackson

PhD Candidate Colorado School of Mines MIRRORLab

☑ rbjackso@mines.edu⅙ rbjackson.github.ioCV updated April 2021

Advised by Dr. Tom Williams, my current research interests include human-robot interaction (particularly verbal noncompliance and clarification interactions), robot ethics, natural language generation (especially pragmatics), people's natural application of socially constructed identity attributes (like gender, race, and class) to artificial entities, and attribution of (moral and social) agency and identity to artificial entities.

#### Education

2018-Present Ph.D. Computer Science, Colorado School of Mines.

Adviser: Dr. Tom Williams

GPA: 4.0

2016–2018 M.S. Computer Science, Colorado School of Mines.

Adviser: Dr. Tracy Camp

GPA: 4.0

2012–2016 B.A. Computer Science, Colorado College.

Discrete Math Minor

GPA: 3.96

### Teaching

2018-2019 TA for Computer Vision

2018 Instructor for Computer Science 101

2017 Instructor for Introduction to Linux

2017–2018 Made and graded midterm and final exams for Computer Simulation

#### Conference Publications

2021 An Integrated Approach to Context-Sensitive Moral Cognition In Robot Cognitive Architectures.

**Ryan Blake Jackson**, Sihui Li, Santosh Balajee Banisetty, Sriram Siva, Hao Zhang, Neil Dantam, and Tom Williams

Under review at the 2021 IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)

2020 Exploring the Role of Gender in Perceptions of Robotic Noncompliance.

Ryan Blake Jackson, Tom Williams, and Nicole M. Smith

Proceedings of the 15th ACM/IEEE International Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI)

2020 "Excuse Me, Robot": Impact of Polite Robot Wakewords on Human-Robot Politeness.

Tom Williams, Daniel Grollman, Mingyuan Han, **Ryan Blake Jackson**, Jane Lockshin, Ruchen Wen, Zachary Nahman, and Qin Zhu International Conference on Social Robotics (ICSR)

2019 Language-Capable Robots may Inadvertently Weaken Human Moral Norms.

Ryan Blake Jackson and Tom Williams

Proceedings of the Companion of the 14th ACM/IEEE International Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI)

2019 Tact in Noncompliance: The Need for Pragmatically Apt Responses to Unethical Commands.

Ryan Blake Jackson, Ruchen Wen, and Tom Williams

Proceedings of the AAAI/ACM Conference on Artificial Intelligence, Ethics, and Society (AIES)

2018 Robot: Asker of Questions and Changer of Norms?.

Ryan Blake Jackson and Tom Williams

Proceedings of the International Conference on Robot Ethics and Standards (ICRES)

2018 A Bayesian Analysis of Moral Norm Malleability during Clarification Dialogues.

Tom Williams, Ryan Blake Jackson, and Jane Lockshin

Proceedings of the 40th annual meeting of the Cognitive Science Society (COGSCI)

2018 Amazon Echo Security: Machine Learning to Classify Encrypted Traffic.

Ryan Blake Jackson and Tracy Camp

27th International Conference on Computer Communication and Networks (ICCCN)

2017 Anomaly Detection in Earth Dam and Levee Passive Seismic Data Using Multivariate Gaussian.

Wendy Fisher, **Ryan Blake Jackson**, Tracy Camp, and Valeria V. Krzhizhanovskaya 16th IEEE International Conference on Machine Learning and Applications (ICMLA)

#### Journal Publications

2021 A Theory of Social Agency for Human-Robot Interaction.

Ryan Blake Jackson and Tom Williams

Under review at Frontiers in Robotics and AI

2021 Enabling Morally Sensitive Robotic Clarification Requests.

Ryan Blake Jackson and Tom Williams

Under review at ACM Transactions on Human-Robot Interaction (THRI)

2021 Why and How Robots Should Say 'No'.

Gordon Briggs, **Ryan Blake Jackson**, Matthias Scheutz, and Tom Williams Accepted at the International Journal of Social Robotics (IJSR) but not yet published

2020 Blame-Laden Moral Rebukes and the Morally Competent Robot: A Confucian Ethical Perspective.

Qin Zhu, Tom Williams, **Ryan Blake Jackson**, and Ruchen Wen Science and Engineering Ethics (S&EE)

## Workshop Publications

2021 On the Flexibility of Robot Social Identity Performance: Benefits, Ethical Risks and Open Research Questions for HRI.

Katie Winkle, **Ryan Blake Jackson**, Alexa Bejarano, and Tom Williams Workshop on Robo-Identity: Artificial identity and multi-embodiment at HRI 2021

Design, Performance, and Perception of Robot Identity.
 Ryan Blake Jackson, Alexa Bejarano, Katie Winkle, and Tom Williams
 Workshop on Robo-Identity: Artificial identity and multi-embodiment at HRI 2021

2020 Identity Performance in Multi-Robot Distributed Systems.

Tom Williams, Daniel Ayers, Camille Kaufman, Jon Emmanuel Serrano, Shania Jo Runningrabbit, Sayanti Roy, Poulomi Pal, Alexandra Bejarano, and **Ryan Blake Jackson** 

Workshop on Human-Robot Interaction for Space Robotics at the 12th International Conference on Social Robotics (ICSR-HRI-SR)

2020 Enabling Morally Sensitive Robotic Clarification Requests.

Ryan Blake Jackson and Tom Williams

Eighth Annual Conference on Advances in Cognitive Systems (ACS)

2019 On Perceived Social and Moral Agency in Natural Language Capable Robots.

Ryan Blake Jackson and Tom Williams

HRI Workshop on The Dark Side of Human-Robot Interaction: Ethical Considerations and Community Guidelines for the Field of HRI

2019 Towards A Role Ethics Approach to Command Rejection.

Ruchen Wen, **Ryan Blake Jackson**, Tom Williams, and Qin Zhu HRI Workshop on The Dark Side of Human-Robot Interaction: Ethical Considerations and Community Guidelines for the Field of HRI

#### Abstracts and Presentations

2019 Generating Appropriate Responses to Inappropriate Robot Commands. Ryan Blake Jackson

Proceedings of the Student Program of the 2nd AAAI/ACM Conference on Artificial Intelligence, Ethics, and Society (AIES)

2019 Toward Morally Sensitive Robotic Communication.

Ryan Blake Jackson

Proceedings of the Human-Robot Interaction (HRI) Pioneers Workshop

2018 Challenges in Responding to Malicious Robot-Directed Commands.

Ryan Blake Jackson and Tom Williams

Extended Abstracts of the Robotics: Science and Systems Workshop on Adversarial Robotics

# 2018 Blame-Laden Moral Rebukes and the Morally Competent Robot: A Confucian Ethical Perspective.

Qin Zhu, Tom Williams, and Ryan Blake Jackson

Proceedings of the Workshop on Brain-Based and Artificial Intelligence

#### Research Positions

2016-Present Research Assistant, Colorado School of Mines.

Contributed to research on various departmental grant projects and publications. Mentored several undergraduates working on various projects.

2016–2018 Master's Thesis Research, Colorado School of Mines.

Investigated machine learning to extract ostensibly private information from data moving between an Echo device and Amazon's servers, despite encryption. Explored determining what type of user request is being answered by the Echo and who, of a finite set of people, is speaking to the Echo.

Summer 2017 Machine Learning Intern, Ricoh Production Print Solutions LLC.

Created a machine learning system to predict production print performance from document traits. System used by sales team to respond to customer inquiries.

2015–2016 Senior Capstone Research Project, Colorado College.

Performed detailed statistical analysis of multithreading context switch data from various operating systems. Presented and defended analysis to suggest kernel optimizations.

Summer 2015 **Undergraduate Researcher**, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Parallel Computing Institute.

Researched machine learning for astrophysics to determine relative velocities of galaxies and properties of dark energy. Presented technical poster summarizing research.

#### Honors and Awards

2020 EAAI-20 New and Future AI Educator Award

Tenth Symposium on Educational Advances in Artificial Intelligence

2020 Best Poster

Computing-Mines Affiliates Partnership Program (C-MAPP)

2019 Accepted participant

HRI Pioneers Graduate Student Consortium

2019 Accepted participant

AIES Graduate Student Consortium

2018 Best Poster Runner Up

Computing-Mines Affiliates Partnership Program (C-MAPP)

2016 **Florian Cajori Award** for outstanding mathematical prowess Colorado College

2016 Graduated Magna Cum Laude

Colorado College

2016 Departmental Distinction in Computer Science

Colorado College

# Selected Professional Service

- 2021 Reviewer for ACM Transactions on Human-Robot Interaction (THRI)
- 2020 Reviewer for the 2021 HRI Pioneers Graduate Student Consortium
- 2020 Reviewer for the 2020 RSS Pioneers Doctoral Consortium
- 2020 Reviewer for the International Conference on Social Robotics (ICSR)
- 2020 Panel Chair for the Human-Robot Interaction (HRI) Pioneers Graduate Student Consortium
- 2019 Reviewer of multiple papers for the 15th ACM/IEEE International Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI-2020)
- 2018–2020 Met with and evaluated faculty candidates
  - 2016 Instructed educational computer science Summer camps for local elementary/middle school students
  - 2016 Instructed professional development workshops for K-12 computer science educators

#### References

#### Dr. Tom Williams

Colorado School of Mines
Department of Computer Science
Email: twilliams@mines.edu

#### Dr. Tracy Camp

Colorado School of Mines Department of Computer Science Email: tcamp@mines.edu

#### Dr. Qin Zhu

Colorado School of Mines Department of Humanities, Arts, and Social Sciences Email: qzhu@mines.edu